[Music]
Hello, everyone! I'm Miss Rebecca. Welcome back to Family Sunday School.
This time we're going to review what we talked about last time.
Last time we talked about Last Supper.
And one of the points, one of the themes was "Jesus is the Bread of Life."
Last time we talked about a lot of buns, right?
Have you played the bun game?
Have you learned that there are many different cultures and people all over the world that need buns?
I'll give you a book to read. It's a cover and there's a little bit of content in it.
I'm using this book for my kids to read.
But you can also use other books in the library about buns or how to make buns.
This book actually talks about a lot of different kinds of buns.
If I give you a quick summary, you'll know how people need buns.
Why is the bun in Last Supper so important?
The symbolism of the bun is that it represents Jesus' body.
Jesus' body represents the bun.
Why?
We need to look at Old Testament.
In Old Testament, the God/Goddess was tied up by the Egyptians.
When they were slaves, they were God/Goddess.
They were taken out of Egypt.
They were taken out of Egypt and they could leave Egypt.
Leave slavery, flee Egypt.
They crossed the Red Sea. Moses crossed the Red Sea.
God/Goddess walked across the Red Sea.
They had to wait.
Wait for when to make a promise.
What did they eat?
God/Goddess said,
"It's better to be a slave. At least I have food. I'm starving."
God/Goddess heard them complain.
If God/Goddess could bring you out of Egypt, what else couldn't God/Goddess do?
At that time, manna would fall from the sky.
It's like a food bun falling from the sky.
In Old Testament, we see that the bun, the manna,
if you eat it, you will be full that day.
But it doesn't mean you won't die.
Fast forward to the New Testament.
The Savior has come.
Jesus is born.
If you eat the bun, you will live forever.
Very different, right?
What kind of bun can live forever?
Pineapple bun? No.
Hamburger bun? No.
The rabbit bun? No.
The cow bun? No.
Only Jesus.
So why did Jesus tell the disciples,
"My body is like a bun.
If you eat this bun, you will live forever."
Because he knew the culture and the history of the bun.
He remembered to slowly connect with it.
Okay, this is the bun.
Next one.
The second point I mentioned last time is
Do you remember Judas left the group to betray Jesus?
Remember? Jesus' family.
I asked you last time,
Why did Judas do that?
What will happen next?
Jesus knew.
Why did he do that?
Why did he allow that?
Remember?
This is the great saving plan.
God's great plan to save people.
God's plan must be fulfilled.
God said he would do it.
Jesus said it would happen.
It will happen.
But does it have to be so bad?
We will continue the story today.
Answer a lot of different questions.
And refer to different points.
I will ask you questions too.
But before we start, let's play a game.
Come with me.
Hello, let's play a game.
What am I?
I will show you different photos.
Ready?
Hmm, a wheel.
Hmm, a screw.
Hmm, what is this?
Can you guess?
Let's start.
Art rack.
We need to dry our paintings in art class.
There are many art class teachers.
You can dry many paintings in this rack.
You can open and close it.
Okay?
Next one.
What am I?
Focus.
Hmm.
Can you guess?
Hmm, what is this?
Hmm.
Hmm, what is this angle?
What angle is this?
Hmm.
Can you guess?
Hmm, a big circle.
What is this?
Let's start.
It's a stool.
Ha ha.
Can you see?
This is the seat.
This is the angle.
This stool can be turned.
This is the screw.
This is the plate.
This is a foot.
Ha ha.
Okay, next one.
I guess you can guess.
Let's start.
Hmm, what is this?
It looks old.
Hmm.
This is the screw.
This is not the screw.
This is a nut.
Hmm.
Hmm?
What is this?
What is the hint in this picture?
This angle is a bit different.
What is this?
Can you guess?
Let's start.
Maybe many children have not seen this.
Or adults, parents have seen it.
Okay, let's start.
Radiator.
It's a radiator.
It's not a central air radiator.
There are many gadgets on the side.
This is the angle.
This is the coil.
This is the switch.
This is the big screw.
Wow.
We have so many "What am I?"
I want to remind you.
Hmm.
If you look at it from different angles,
you can't see the whole picture from every angle.
Right?
We think with this mentality.
We will talk about the Bible story.
Perspective.
Point of view.
Angle.
Alright?
Bible story time.
Hi, it's story time.
Where did we leave off last time?
Where did Jesus tell Judas,
"Do what you have to do."
What did Judas do?
He betrayed Jesus.
Telling others where Jesus is.
Because many leaders don't want Jesus there.
They want Jesus to leave.
But they can't find Jesus.
They are afraid.
Because the public loves Jesus.
They like him.
Because he did a lot of good things.
But they can't find out where he is.
Only the people inside will know.
Right?
In this video,
Judas went to find Jesus.
Jesus went outside.
He called other leaders.
"The time is here."
"I will be caught."
"You have to protect yourselves."
"Don't sleep."
"Pray to the Lord to help you."
"You can resist all the attacks."
"All the temptations."
But they fell asleep.
Jesus started praying.
He asked God,
"I know this plan must be fulfilled."
"But if it is possible, can we not do it?"
"But I know your will is my command."
"God, whatever you want."
He finished praying.
What happened next?
Judas told the soldiers,
"Hey, the one I love is Jesus."
Wow!
Let's see.
This is Judas.
The people next to him.
"I know this is Jesus."
Not everyone has seen Jesus.
Not everyone knows who to catch.
Now he knows.
What happened next?
Peter.
Jesus said to Peter,
"Peter, you will deny me."
"Pretend not to know."
"Deny."
"You know me."
"You pretend not to know me."
"Of course it's not me."
"Never."
This is Peter.
He picked up a sword.
Jesus said, "Protect yourselves."
"Bring the swords."
"Because there will be an attack."
Before, they went around with Jesus.
They talked to people.
They didn't need swords.
Now they need them.
Peter took out his sword.
What did he say?
He didn't say anything.
He just cut open the soldier's ear.
First, was his aim good?
Wow, he cut it open.
I don't think the soldier expected this.
But we know from Peter's perspective,
from his perspective,
he loves Jesus very much.
He loves Jesus very much.
He is a good friend.
He must defend Jesus.
No matter what, he will protect Jesus.
"Hiyah!"
What do you think of Jesus?
"Put the sword down."
"Put the sword down, Peter."
The soldier's ear was cut off.
Remember, he was bleeding.
He was bleeding.
Ouch, it hurts.
What does Jesus do?
He didn't take him to the hospital.
He didn't need stitches.
He didn't need to do much.
He just put his hand on the soldier's ear.
Healed.
Right?
If Jesus can be blind,
he can also be able to see.
If he can cut off the soldier's ear,
Wow.
Jesus said,
"I have to go."
"This is part of the plan."
"This has to happen."
"I just had last supper with you."
Look, Jesus followed the soldier.
"Arrest."
He arrested him.
We are in the modern world.
In the modern world,
what is "arrest"?
Right?
Is it tying his hands?
Or using a rope?
Or carrying him out?
No, no, no.
The Bible says,
Jesus followed them.
He allowed them to arrest him.
Because if Jesus didn't allow it,
how could he do it?
He could cut off his ear
and touch it.
He could do it.
But if he tied his hands,
tied his hands,
he couldn't tie him up.
Big point here.
Right?
Hmm.
I wonder.
What are these two soldiers
thinking?
From their perspective,
what's happening?
What are they thinking of?
From their perspective,
they are thinking,
"Hey, we are here to arrest you."
"By accident,
someone cut off your ear."
"The blood is flowing."
"But I want to arrest that person."
"Wow,
he is a fake."
"He is not a real son of God."
"Why did he touch my ear
and it healed?"
Hmm.
We said
we should think from perspective.
Right?
I will give you some time.
Let's talk about it.
This soldier
was cut off his ear.
He was touched by Jesus.
His ear healed.
But what about this soldier?
Remember,
this story is about
perspective.
Angle.
Point of view.
From different angles,
we see the same thing.
Just like the game.
We will understand
the whole story
more completely.
The Bible did not say
how this soldier
saw the story.
But we can think about it.
We can guess.
We can imagine.
Right?
I will pause the video
with this question.
If you are
this soldier,
you see so many things.
What is your perspective?
What is your story?
What will you think?
What will you say to your wife
when you get home?
What will you say to your children
What will you say to yourself?
Pause. Discuss.
I told you to pause.
Why did you pause?
Pause. Discuss.
What will this soldier see?
What angle?
Perspective.
He has different perspective from Peter.
Different perspective from Judas.
Right?
I expect you paused.
I will discuss with you again.
Here we go. Let's continue the story.
Do you remember who said,
"Jesus, where are you going?
I will follow you."
Do you remember who said that?
Yes. Peter.
And do you remember
who said that?
When we first started talking about the story,
the story of Last Supper,
Jesus asked this soldier to set up a table
for the people to eat.
Who was that?
John.
John is often
the one
who loves the most
in the Bible.
The one who Jesus loved.
That was John.
What will they do?
After all these things happened,
what will they do?
What will they do?
Can you see where they are?
Look!
There is John.
He is the youngest
among the people.
Youngest.
Who is this?
Peter is holding a sword.
They are following him.
Right?
His beloved Jesus was taken away.
But what are they forgetting?
What is he forgetting?
Who is this?
Jesus!
Jesus was taken away
by them.
Do you think Jesus will be in trouble?
Do you think
what will John and Peter
do next?
What are they thinking now?
Let's talk about this
when we debrief.
This is the end of the story.
We will continue next time.
We just finished
the story of the Bible.
Today's topic is
perspective.
Point of view.
Now, let's think about
the story just now.
If we look at it from different perspectives,
different perspectives,
different point of view,
from different perspectives,
there are many different angles.
Do you remember our game?
We have many different perspectives
to build a comprehensive story.
If we don't have a comprehensive story
or we can't see it in detail,
we are not comprehensive enough.
Right?
In the Bible,
when Jesus was taken away,
when Jesus prayed
in the garden,
there are many different accounts
in the Gospel.
In the Gospel,
we see
there is Luke,
John, Matthew, Mark.
But if we
can use our brain
to think from different angles,
what will we think?
Although
it is not necessarily mentioned in the Bible
that John has a perspective,
because John is
an author in the Gospel.
He is a writer.
We can also see
a little bit of Jesus' perspective
because he is in the garden.
Right?
We can imagine Peter's perspective.
We can also imagine
Judas' perspective.
Let's take some time
to think about it together.
First, we have
Jesus.
So, pretend.
假設你是Jesus
Hello, my name is Jesus.
現在發生這件事,你會想什麼?
If you were Jesus,
what would your story be like?
如果你是耶穌的時候,
你的故事會怎樣變?
你的角度會怎樣?
從Jesus的角度
會怎樣看這個故事?
Pause
想一想
再回來,我告訴你
One version of
耶穌可能會有
這樣的角度來看
第一個
If I were Jesus
記得我們看到他在
花園裏面嗎?
他還在祈禱
他的角度就是
A bit of
什麼?
Exhausted
是不是? 很累喔
神啊
如果你這個計劃
可以沒有這一部分
可不可以呢?
這麼辛苦,可不可以呢?
其實,耶穌
會不會真的很累?
他做了這麼多神蹟,救了這麼多人
但也有人
要追殺他
還有門徒好像
怎麼說都不明白
叫他不要睡覺
祈禱
因為那些人會來抓我
要保護自己
祈禱完,發生什麼事?
睡不著
他的角度,耶穌的角度
會怎麼說這個故事呢?
我們想起
Judas,即是出賣耶穌的那位
用錢來交換
告訴別人
耶穌是誰的那位Judas
我們未必很清楚
當時的那一刻
出賣耶穌
出賣耶穌之前,他在想什麼
但我們可以幻想
我們可以想想
如果假設我們是Judas
我們會在想什麼呢?
我就帶他們去找耶穌
我親那口,那個男人
那個就是耶穌
就是這麼多
哇!
剛剛親完他
彼得就去
把那個男人的耳朵切下來
不知道是不是很壞呢?
耶穌還救回那個soldier
還弄好他的耳朵
覺得很矛盾
為了這麼少錢
出賣耶穌
好像很壞
我們再想想
如果從另一個角度來看
另一個角度
第二個觀點
彼得
彼得就是
把耳朵切下來的那個
記得他嗎?
就是那個
耶穌,你去到邊,我跟你去邊
耶穌,你死,我跟你去死
我永遠是你的朋友
我不會否認你的
I won't deny you
到這個地步
如果彼得要說這個故事
他會怎麼說呢?
你們休息一下
你們大家談吧
如果我是彼得
我怎麼會說這個故事呢?
我怎麼重複給人聽呢?
If I were Peter
How would I tell the story?
是啊
耶穌就祈禱完
找我們滿堂
但是很失望,我們又睡著了
他明明叫我們不要睡
叫我們祈禱
但是,期期下,真的很累
我都不以為我會睡覺
由這麼多人之中
我當然要為了耶穌祈禱
當然要為了大眾祈禱
但是,又不是睡著了
之後,哇,大件事了
朱迪斯來
親了耶穌一口
帶了一些不知道什麼軍人來
抓耶穌
哇,真是大件事
但是呢
我呢,就不會
站著不做事的
生氣得我
拿著劍
斬了那個軍人
蘇州的議席下來
怎麼樣?生氣吧
這樣對待耶穌
耶穌做了多少好事
耶穌愛多少人
這樣對待他,不得了
不行,我是不會容許的
對了
又是衰衝動
又是衝動
耶穌就說,叫我放下劍
這樣,很厲害
他一碰那個人的耳朵
哇,明明在那裡流血
這樣碰一碰,好像
魔術
但是,耶穌不是魔術師
耶穌是神的兒子,就是神
當然可以治好,對吧?
哇,治好了,叫我放下劍
那我當然
聽聽話,放下劍
但是,我還是不服
我也要跟蹤他們
看他帶耶穌去哪裡
我會永遠跟著他
永遠跟著耶穌
看他帶他去哪裡
OK,現在有很多
不同的角度看,對吧?
剩下誰?
John,是不是剩下約翰?
對了,John就是
剛開始的故事
他幫人
設置桌子,對吧?
耶穌叫他擺好位置
我們要吃 Passover
乖乖地,你知道John
是全部
門徒之中最小的
經常John寫
福音的時候
他說
Jesus is most loved, Jesus is beloved
就是耶穌最疼的那位
其實我們看到他的故事
玩到
Love, and follow,對吧?
那如果他
故事怎麼說呢?我們其實知道
因為聖經裡面
有John的帳號
我們可以讀,但是假設
如果你是John
你會怎麼看呢?
關一鈊,你們聊聊
回來
我給你我的版本
我的版本給你聽
但是我們有聖經可以看
可以看John
是有哪些細節有
哪些細節沒有
如果我是John
If I were John
我會怎麼說這個故事呢?
OK
耶穌祈禱完就出來
我就
起了身
我已經睡了
然後很多事發生
明明
要跟隨耶穌
去很多不同地方
為什麼有這麼多事發生?
吃
吃宵夜之前
祂就每個人幫我們洗腳
哇
祂真的很疼我們
之後又說了很多事
說祂要走
說我們要吃祂的身體
要吃麵包
喝酒
喝酒要吃祂的血
說著說著
都好像重複很多不同的東西
但是又不是太清楚
祂想說什麼
祂出來祈禱
不知道祂想說什麼
貿貿然
來了一個Judas
Judas吃了他一口
彼得又
割了人家耳朵
耶穌又救了他
又治好他
然後耶穌就
跟著那兩個軍人走
只是這樣走
跟著他們走
我就很愛耶穌
耶穌那麼疼我
我當然要跟蹤他們
看他們帶我和耶穌去哪裡
我一定會在他們旁邊
他們那麼疼我
我一定會聽他們的話
他們一定有東西要告訴我們
知道是什麼來的
因為
我們那麼愛他們
他們那麼愛我們
一定要跟蹤他們
慢慢小心地跟蹤他們
OK
我們回想起來
有那麼多不同的角度的時候
你覺不覺得這個故事
這樣看是比較全面一點呢
我們不會知道
為什麼有某些部分
聖經裏面沒有說
為什麼某些角度聖經沒有說
但是我們作為人
我們作為想到東西的人
感覺到東西的人
其實可以幻想的
我們讀其他故事書也是
是不是
如果讀Three Little Pigs
那我說
如果一個狼說一個故事
會怎麼說一個故事呢
那變了是你可以
不同的角度去看一個故事
好像我們玩的遊戲一樣
你反轉一個故事
來參考、來了解
反轉看一個比較深入的細節
你會看到些什麼呢
看到很多不同的東西
我們可以求神
祈禱說神啊
幫我們看到這個故事
雖然很多次聽過這個故事
但是如果用不同的角度來看
可以
多認識一些東西
可以了解你多少呢
求你幫我們
謝謝耶穌
故事怎麼繼續
耶穌跟了那兩個軍人去哪
之後會發生什麼事
哇
下一集再說
OK 大家準備好了嗎
中文時間
我整個episode
就講角度
Perspective
Angle
其實中文角度
即是甚麼意思呢
其實就是
角度
中文角度即是甚麼意思呢
角
角度即是角
Corner
度
角度
你可以說
一個triangle
三角形
三
一二三
三個角
Three corners
三個angle
角度
角度和
角
同樣的
周圍看看
你周圍的東西
哪些有角呢
甚麼東西有角呢
我就叫我兒子去找
你們可以
拍住他
OK
我叫我兒子去找東西有角
甚麼東西有角呢
你告訴別人
你找到這本書的角在哪
這裡
即是corner
這裡有角
這本書的形狀
是長方形
長方形有多少個角呢
How many
四個
你數吧
一二三
四
四個角
角又可以想corner
角又可以找角度
angle
或者perspective
在我的可以
例子就是在我的角度
來看
我覺得
應該日日吃雪糕
So from my point of view
From my angle
I think everyday we should eat ice cream
Who thumbs up
You agree
但或者媽咪會講
唔係喎
從媽咪的角度來看
日日食雪糕
唔健康喎
媽咪says wait
From a mom's point of view
Eating ice cream everyday
Isn't healthy
Or
Agree
Disagree
Or so so
我們可以有唔同個角度
Let's see
What else is a 角
Corner
Street corner
街角
So when you say I'll meet you at the corner
我喺街角等你啦
Corner
角
Right
And then when you go to the corner
Stand in the corner
Or put it at the corner
角一頭都係有個角字
Challenge
If
如果三角形
Triangle
係叫三角形
Hexagon
係乜嘢
中文hexagon
係點講
下次你答我
See you later
Bye
大家而家到返
At home extension
喺屋企點樣可以深入啲
講呢個故事俾小朋友聽呢
我就呼籲大家
攞返大型嘅成經
Your Bible
去返John 18
約翰第十八章
讀返嗰度係講返Jesus is Arrest
之前都可以睇返
Last Supper 嗰啲
我就想你讀俾小朋友聽
或者一齊讀都好
讀完就想問你哋
睇下
Miss Rebecca 做嗰個
edition, 嗰個 version
Of John 嘅角度
同其實神想我哋讀John
嘅角度有啲咩出入
有啲咩唔同呢
點解
One, Teacher Rebecca 係幻想
但係喺
聖經裏面嗰個 perspective
嗰個角度 from John
咁就我哋知
亦都可以講俾小朋友聽
其實福音, Gospel 有四個 account
係咪?
都係可以講緊 Last Supper
都係可以講緊 Jesus is Arrest
都係可以講緊 Easter Story
點解要四個呢?
有
Matthew, Mark, Luke 同埋 John
一個咪夠囉
點解要咁多個?
嗱, The Bible 唔會錯㗎嘛
係咪?
連 Easter Story 嘅 Gospel 都有四個 account
證明
神都想我哋睇唔同個角度嘅嘢
係咪?
抽出唔同嘢出嚟
係一個 story 都可以抽出唔同嘅嘢
變咗點呀?
嗰個 story 會有多啲意思, more meaning
嗰個 story 會豐富啲, richer
[Music]